Finding Aid for Lillian Gill papers, 1950s-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lillian Gill papers 1950s-2007
Gill, Lillian.
6 linear feet
2008001 Aa 2
African American businesswoman from Grand Rapids, Michigan; correspondence, clippings, published materials, and photographs largely relating to her civic, political, fraternal, and church activities, especially her long-time involvement with the Order of the Eastern Star and with New Hope Baptist Church in Grand Rapids.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Lillian Gill (donor no. 9933 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions in 2007.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lillian Gill was born in Mississippi but later moved to Grand Rapids, Michigan in 1936. She is a businesswoman who worked selling Nutrilite Food Supplement (now part of the Amway Corporation) and insurance underwriter for the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company and the Great Lakes Mutual Life Insurance Company.
Much of her life has been devoted to religious, civic, political, and fraternal activities and organizations. She has been a long-time member of New Hope Baptist Church in Grand Rapids and has participated in state and regional African American Baptists organizations, notably the Western District Association of Baptist Churches of Michigan and the General Baptist State Convention of Michigan.
In politics, Lillian Gill has been active in local Democratic party affairs and has participated in various local elections, notably as a candidate to serve as delegate to Michigan's Constitutional Convention in 1961.
An extremely energetic woman, Gill was also active in the Order of the Eastern Star, affiliate of the International Free and Accepted Modern Masons. She participated both locally in the Queen Esther Chapter and on the state and national level. She has been Grand Matron of Michigan, Illustrious Grand Matron, and Supreme Sovereign of Stars among other positions.
The Lillian Gill collection is comprised of the following series: Biographical and personal; Business career; Political and community interests; Order of Eastern Star, Free and Accepted Modern Masons; New Hope Baptist Church and other Baptist organizations; and Photographs. The great bulk of the collection details her Masonic responsibilities and her activities with her church and with her denomination's regional and state organization. Much of these series consist of printed material, including bulletins, brochures, programs, announcements, and the like. A smaller portion of the collection relates to her varied business endeavors as an insurance underwriters and as a salesperson with Amway. There is also slight material relating to her political and civil rights involvement with the local chapter of the NAACP.
Subjects:
African American Baptists--Michigan.; African American Baptists--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; African American freemasonry.; African American freemasons.; African American women--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Amway Corporation.; General Baptist State Convention of Michigan.; Gill, Lillian.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Church history.; Great Lakes Mutual Life Insurance Company.; New Hope Baptist Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Order of the Eastern Star.; Western District Association.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African American women--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Amway Corporation.; Gill, Lillian.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); New Hope Baptist Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Order of the Eastern Star.; Fraternal organizations--United States.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical and personal
  - Vita, biographical sketches (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical notes and writings (Box 1)
  - Poetry (Box 1)
  - Awards and other recognitions (Box 1)
  - Citations and certificates (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Oakdale School, appearance at school (Box 1)
  - Robert Gill (son) -- cartoonist and teacher (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous personal (Box 1)
- Business Career
  (mainly publications and other printed material)
  - Nutrilite / Amway (Box 1)
  - Life Underwriter Training Council Course workbooks, 2 binders (Box 1)
  - North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Mutual Life Insurance Company (Box 1)
- Political and Community Interests
  - Grand Rapids National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (Box 1)
  - Michigan Constitutional Convention, campaign for delegate 1961 (Box 1)
  - Model Cities Temporary Committee 1968 (Box 1)
- Order of Eastern Star, Free and Accepted Modern Masons
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and other mailings (Box 2)
  - Correspondence -- Nassau, Bahamas (Box 2)
  - Doctrines, training materials, constitutions (Box 2)
  - Grand Matrons Council (Box 2)
  - Programs, Supreme Convention, International F. & A.M. Masons and Order of Eastern Star
    - 1960-1990, 2 expandable folders (Box 2)
    - 1991-2005, 1 expandable folder (Box 3)
  - Programs of state conventions and banquets of Exalted Degree Department annual conclaves
    - 1954-2006, 3 expandable folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous programs and related, 3 expandable folders (Box 4)
  - Masonic calendars (Box 4)
  - Masonic newspapers and newsletters (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
- New Hope Baptist Church and other Baptist organizations
  - Activity calendars (Box 5)
  - Anniversary booklets (Box 5)
  - Annual reports (Box 5)
  - Background and informational material (Box 5)
  - Building program (Box 5)
  - Business meetings and financial reports (Box 5)
  - Clippings (Box 5)
  - Williams -- Dr. John V. Williams anniversary brochures (Box 5)
  - Church bulletins, 2 expandable folders (Box 5)
  - Other New Hope publications (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - General Baptist State Convention of Michigan, programs and other published materials (Box 6)
  - Western District Association, programs and other published materials (Box 6)
  - Other Michigan churches, published materials (Box 6)
  - Out-of-state church materials (Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Amway meetings (Box 6)
  - Masonic activities, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - New Hope Baptist Church (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Snapshots (various activities and functions), 2 expandable folders (Box 6)